<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers no deceivers, or, The management of an unjust charge against them confuted. Being a brief return to a pamphlet, intituled, The Quakers proved deceivers ... by John Horne ... / by one who is counted a deceiver, yet true, George Whitehead.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47683548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47683548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96398)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2661:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers no deceivers, or, The management of an unjust charge against them confuted. Being a brief return to a pamphlet, intituled, The Quakers proved deceivers ... by John Horne ... / by one who is counted a deceiver, yet true, George Whitehead.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>33 [i.e. 35], p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horn, John, 1614-1676. --  Quakers proved deceivers.</term>
               <term>Quakers proved deceivers.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173002:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE QUAKERS NO Deceivers, Or the Management of an unjuſt Charge againſt them Confuted.</p>
            <p>BEING A BRIEF RETURN to a Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>The Quakers Proved Deceivers, and ſuch as the People ought not to liſten to or follow but to account Accurſed, in the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Charge given out againſt them to that effect, By</hi> John Horne, <hi>who calls Himſelf Preacher of the Goſpel at</hi> South-Lin <hi>in</hi> Norfolke, <hi>who is a chief Teacher among the People called</hi> Mooreans <hi>or</hi> Univerſaliſts.</p>
            <p>Who hath given forth a pretended and imperfect Relation of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which was between him and <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> in the Chancel of <hi>South-Lin,</hi> wherin he hath falſely made his boaſt, how that he made good his ſaid Charge againſt <hi>G.W.</hi> before ſome Hundreds of people; but many unprejudiced perſons who heard the Diſcourſe between them, can witneſſe againſt the ſaid <hi>I.H.</hi> as a vain Boaſter in his Pride, of a Victory where he had it not.</p>
            <p>And herein i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid <hi>J. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne</hi> proved to be ſuch a one, as he hath falſely charged the Quak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs proved to be, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is falſe Doctrines, touching ſeveral things of much Concernment Diſcovere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and his ſlanders and perverting the Truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and the Truth of God cleared. For the Information of the People cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Univerſaliſts, and other Profeſſors and People.</p>
            <p>See PSAL. 7.14, 15.</p>
            <p>By one who is counted a Deceiver, yet true, <hi>George Whitehead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black-Spread-Eagle, near the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:173002:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173002:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Leſſed are they that are not offended at the truth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bide in the love of it as it is made manifeſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> who live in the life and power of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h fathomes over and comprehends the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rpent, which greatly appears theſe our d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſeed of God, and the wiſdoms and power of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing manifeſt in a large meaſure in his Servants, which gives them dominion in the life, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency to reign over the haters of the truth, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to diſcover all their ſubtilty and crafts; this is their torment and vexation, and the more they ſtrive againſt the truth which we are in, the more they are drowned in their confuſion, and overwhelmed in their darkneſs: Therefore let us whom the Lord hath called into his work, go on in the name and power of our God, with boldneſs and confidence in him in this day of the Lambs battel, for the Lord is with us; and it is in his ſtrength that we are made able to tread over our enemies: and to trample over all their malignity and deceits, which they appear in againſt the truth of our God which is dear unto us, and after many conteſts and much oppoſition which we have paſſed thorow, and met with from the deceivers of many ſorts in this age, who are of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons Armie, who like their Leader are wroth with the ſeed of the Woman which keeps the Commands of God. I have of late time met with one <hi>Iohn Horn</hi> one of the ſame Army, who hath ſhewed his rage and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as much againſt the truth, both in his Books and Papers as any that ever I met with, and his torment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing begun his rage and malice is the greater; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by many he is had in reputation, and ſet up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Prieſts of the Nation, but hath foamed out
<pb facs="tcp:173002:3"/>his ſhame more then many of them. The occaſion of my laſt diſputing with him (on the 13 day of the 11th moneth, (59) was his poſting up many Papers publikely in <hi>Lin,</hi> wherein he charged the Quakers to be Deceivers, and ſuch as the people ought not to hear or follow, but to account accurſed; and ſaid, that he ſhould be ready to make it good, as and when thereto lawfully called: Upon which I ſeveral times for the Truth ſake ſent to him to come forth in publike, before I could get him ſo out, for he would have had us met at his houſe, or at a friends houſe of his, which was not convenient, for ſuch a meeting as was to be; but at length he proffered to meet me in the Chancel in the Steeple houſe end, where we met, and after I had heard him ſpeak a pretty time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and had ſome liberty to anſwer to ſome of the chief things he objected againſt us, we had ſome diſcourſe about ſeveral weighty things; as freedom from ſin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the new-born ſtate, the redemption of the body, and the coming of Chriſt; and the cheif thing <hi>I. H.</hi> drove at was to make people beleeve, <hi>That there is no man living upon earth that ſinneth not, or that could be perfectly freed from ſin in this life, and that the Proph<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s and Apoſtles had ſin in them ſo long as they l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved,</hi> and ſo he made War for his Fathers Kingdome (which is upheld by ſin) as much as he could, as the reſt of the deceivers chiefly do, and in the power of the Lord, I ſpeake in Vindication of the truth, to clear it from his falſe aſperſions and ſlanders, as much as I might have liberty to; for <hi>I. H.</hi> and ſome of his Company were very uncivil towards me in many of them, clam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uring at once againſt me, but the Lord appeared with me and his truth, which then reached his witneſs in the Conſciences of many, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heard me with ſoberneſs, which as appears was a grief
<pb facs="tcp:173002:3"/>to my adverſary, and as is probable was ſome cauſe of his publiſhing an imperfect Relation of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute in Print, to render me and the truth odious, and in his pride to make people beleeve he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the victory or maiſtery, touching which his vain boaſting and deceit is hereafter diſcovered, and the Truth cleared.</p>
            <p>And now from ſufficient grounds and tryal, I affirm, and can (through the ſtrength of God) make good theſe things againſt the ſaid <hi>J. Horn,</hi> and charge them againſt him as followeth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That he is out of the life and ſteps of the true Miniſters, and in the ſteps and practiſes of Deceivers, and ſo is a Hypocrite, and no Miniſter of Chriſt, who being a Pariſh-prieſt is guilty of the Prieſts iniquity in many things whom he hath declared againſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he upholds a dead and formal Worſhip like the World, whereunto people are not called by the Spirit of truth for it, is not the true Worſhip, ſo that he keeps people from the life of God, his Miniſtry being both dead, formal and corrupt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That his Miniſtry (vvherein he contends for ſin, pleading that none can be perfectly free from it in this life) is Antichriſtian and both againſt the commands, promiſes, and works of God, and tends to the making both the preaching and praying of Chriſt and the Saints ineffectual.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And that he the ſaid <hi>I. H.</hi> (like a cholerick envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man againſt the truth of God and his people) is a forger of lies, a falſe acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, a ſlanderer, and ſo is one of the Dragons Army, who was wroth with the woman that brought forth the man childe, and the remnant of
<pb facs="tcp:173002:4"/>her ſeed that kept the commands of God. Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt charges againſt him are hereafter proved in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Treatiſe, and the reſt with them am I willing to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and make good to his face in publike, where I may be heard, either in the Market place, Steeple-houſe, or our meeting place in <hi>Lin,</hi> or at ſome other publike place in the Country that way if thereunto I be lawfully called, and have an opportunity that way, that the Lord make way for me to it; and if <hi>I. H.</hi> will upon that account meet me, through the ſtrength of God, I am free to do it as he makes way for the Truth ſake, and their ſakes who would knovv it.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:173002:4"/>
               <head>The Management of an unjuſt Charge againſt the Quakers Confuted.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the ſaid <hi>John Horn</hi> the Prieſt hath laid down theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> People, <q>I am come hither to make good a charge formerly laid by me againſt the people called Quakers, <hi>viz.</hi> To prove them to be deceivers, and ſuch as people ought not to hear, or follow, but to account them accurſed, and for proof that there are ſuch he brings, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. And then he ſaith in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> I ſhall pitch upon two heads of trialls. 1. Touching the manner of the coming of the true Prophets and Apoſtles in the way of their doctrine. And, 2. The matter delivered by them therein, for the manner of their coming I ſhall note. 1. That true the Apoſtles and Prophets of God and Chriſt always, uſe to come with abaſements of themſelves in the preſence of God, and with exalting and lifting up God and Chriſt, they uſe to confeſs themſelves ſinners, to be weak and brutiſh in themſelves, as of themſelves; never any of them uſed to vaunte themſelves or ſpeak of themſelves, or one another, as ſinleſs, but alwaies abaſe themſelves and glorifie the Lord, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that come otherwiſe preaching themſelves ſinleſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: and much more that vilifie and Reproach others for confeſing ſin, theſe have not the badges of the true Prophets and Apoſtles, by this we may diſcover this people called Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, (he ſaith) and afterward hath charged us for not coming as the true Prophets and Apoſtles, and then he brings ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Scriptures to prove that the Holy men of God uſe to own themſelves to have ſin in them (or to confeſs ſin,) as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. and 38.16. and 143.2. and 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.2,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173002:5"/>3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6.7. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9, <hi>Iſa</hi> 65.5. and Chap. 59.10, 11, 12, 13. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 14 7, 8 9.20, 21. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.22. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Rom</hi> 7.17.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>James</hi> 3.9. 1. <hi>Job.</hi> 2.1, 2.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To which I Reply, in all which <hi>John Horn</hi> hath proved no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt us called Quakers, nor made it appear that we come not abaſing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as the true Prophets and Apoſtles did, for we own their confeſſing ſin, and have confeſſed ours to the Lord as they did, and are come to deny our ſelves and ſins, but the Holy men of God were not alwaies confeſſing their ſins, as the Prieſts are who make many confeſſions of their ſins and never forſake them, but plead for them and ſo their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions are but feigned, for its ſuch as confeſs their ſins and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them that ſhall find mercy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. And this we wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and herein is Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs exalted, and not our ſelves, and ſo all your feigned confeſſions, and your feigned praying to be cleanſed from your ſins: when ſtill you continue in lin and plead for it, to Remain in all men the tearm of life we deny, knowing that ſuch are out of the life and Spirit of the Prophets and Holy men of God, who ſuffered the terrors of the Lord for ſin, and did confeſs and forſake their ſins knowing the fear of the Lord which is to depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which fear keeps the heart clean, and ſuch as live in it, ſhall not depart from the Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.40. But out of that ſtate are you all ſhut, who continue in ſin, pride, and deceit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for it, who thereby would make all the commands of God, and his promiſes, and works, and the prayers of the Saints of none effect, the end of all which is Righteouſneſs and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo <hi>Iohn Horn</hi> his charging us as being accurſed, and not to be heard will Return upon his own head, as one who hath curſed where God hath bleſſed, and brought an evill Report upon them that fear the Lord, and he hath herein done no leſs ſought to make people hate the judgement of God, and then to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r or follow it, but to account the judgement of God accurſed, according to his own words, for he and <hi>Thomas Moere</hi> have in their diſcovery, acknowledged us (called Quakers) to be a heavy judgement of God that he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to them to puniſh them for their neglect of Chriſt the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God, and the truth of him ſo long abuſed by them, and where he ſaith as that never any of the true Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173002:5"/>uſed to ſpeak of themſelves, or one another as ſinleſs; this is falſe, for the true Prophet ſaid, all his judgements were before me, and as for his ſtatutes I did not depart from them. I was alſo upright before him, and have kept my ſelf from mine iniquity, therefore the Lord hath Recompeuſed me according to my Righteouſneſs, according to my cleanneſs in his eye-ſight, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 22, 23. And the Lord hath promiſed, that his people ſhall be all Righteous and clean from all their filthineſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36 25. And theſe that <hi>John</hi> ſaw on mount <hi>Sion</hi> (to which mount they were come, the Apoſtles writ to in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23.) who followed the Lamb whitherſoever he went, and ſuch Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Kings on the earth; they were without fault before the throne of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4, 5. Chap. 5.10. And ſuch could ſing to the Lord a new ſong, and exalt God, which they that are in their iniquity and pleading for ſin cannot ſing nor exalt for they are enemies to the State of the new creature in Chriſt; where all old things are paſt away &amp; all become new, and ſo with the Spirit of life we ſee thorow the State wherein all are ſinners into the State wherein all that come into Chriſt muſt be Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſo we have a cloud of witneſſes and many true evidences for our Teſtimony that it is of God; and what we hold is truth and all that own God muſt own us therein, who are counted peceivers (as the Saints were) yet true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(John Horn</hi> in page 3. ſaith, True, it is he ſaith in 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17. As he is ſo are we in this world <q>he cannot mean in it we are without ſin as he is, becauſe that is contrary to his own ſaying, that if we ſay we have no ſin we deceive our ſelves, nor will it Reach to all things, for then we might ſay as Chriſt is without a viſible perſonall body in the world, ſubject to aches and pains, and mortality, ſo are we too, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here his deceit and perverting the Scripture is ſeen, and though it cannot be ſaid of <hi>I. H.</hi> and ſuch as he is that they are without ſin as Chriſt is in this world, yet <hi>I ohn</hi> who knew that State wherein they had ſin and in which if they had ſaid they had no ſin they deceived themſelves, he ſaid if we confeſs our ſins, he is faithfull and juſt to forgive us our ſins and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8, 9. So he did not ſay they ſhould have ſin ſo long as they were in this world, for he ſaith little children let no man deceive you he that doth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173002:6"/>Righteouſneſs is Righteous even as he is Righteous, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3, 6, 7. Plainly implying, that they are deceivers who ſay the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that men cannot be without ſin while they are in this world, and ſuch a deceiver is this <hi>Iohn Horn,</hi> and it is evident that when <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith as he is ſo are we in this world, it was in Relation to their dwelling in God and God in them; that they might have have boldneſs in the day of judgment, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.16, 17. And he that abideth in God ſinneth not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I. H.</hi> Saith, you ſee this proved, that the true Apoſtles and Prophets uſe to confeſs ſin in themſelves and none of them to glory in their perfection and ſinleſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the true Apoſtles and Prophets uſe none of them to glory in their perfection, then they uſe not to glory in Chriſt, (who is it will believe this deceit,) for Chriſt was their Righteouſneſs and perfection as he was become all to them who were the Righteouſneſs of God in him, and in him they glorified and Rejoyced. <q>Again <hi>Iohn Horn's</hi> words are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> And this <hi>George White-head</hi> have lately reproached us for joyning our ſelves with the Nation in confeſſing ſin, and that the Quakers are ordered of God as a judgement, to us (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Nation, whereof we are part) for our neglect of Chriſt the ſalvation of God and the abuſe of his truth, how do they inſult over us for this. <hi>G. W.</hi> Among the reſt hath Reproached us for owning our ſelves as part of the Nation guilty of ſin with them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> So this <hi>Iohn Horn</hi> hath owned himſelf, and ſuch as own him to be joyned with the Nation as a part of it guilty of ſin with them, who are neglecters of Chriſt and Abuſers of the truth, when in their other Book againſt us, this <hi>I. H.</hi> and <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> do much exclaime againſt both the Teachers and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation, againſt the Teachers for being ſuch as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11, 12. As blind watchmen unto whom the preaching of the Croſs is a ſealed Book, and they call them dumb dogs that cannot bark, and that love to ſlumber and take their eaſe, and to content themſelves with dreams in ſtead of ſearching out the truth, and that they are doggs ſtrong to appetite, hunting after livings and maintenance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe things and much more have <hi>Iohn Horn</hi> and <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> charged the Prieſts of this Nation with, and they charged the people gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173002:6"/>with neglecting Chriſt and his truth and taking no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure therin, but rather in ſloathfulneſſe, formallity, coveteouſneſs, pride, and vanity in Aparrell, &amp;c. But now marke, for all theſe mens declaring thus againſt the Prieſts, and People of this Nation, they are now joyned with them, and are guilty of ſin with them, as <hi>J.H.</hi> confeſſeth, who hath joyned himſelf with the blind watch-men, and the dumb dogs, who content themſelves with dreames inſtead of truth, and ſo he is guilty of ſin, and a falſe dreamer with them. Oh! what deceit and hippocriſy are theſe men in, one while to declare ſo much againſt the Teachers, and People of this Nation, and another while to joyne with them, as guilty of ſin, and abuſing the truth with them, ſo whether they be fit to teach others or not, any wiſe man may judge. And as for his ſaying that we reproach or villifie them as for confeſſing their neglect of Chriſt, and their abuſe of his truth, herein he miſtakes us. For we witneſſe againſt them for their hyppocriſie, and deceit, and being ſuch abuſers of the truth as they are. And alſo witneſſe againſt them for their ſtriveing againſt the heavy judgment of God, and their revileing and abuſing that judgment which he hath ordered to puniſh them for their neglect of Chriſt, and the truth of him ſo long abuſed by them, which heavy judgment they acknowledge us called <hi>Quakers</hi> to be, and yet they continue revileing and reproaching us, when as they ſhould rather bear the judgment of God patiently, ſeeing they have ſinned ſo much againſt God in their long abuſing his truth, as they have done, and yet do.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And now touching the matter of doctrine <hi>I.H.</hi> chargeth the <q>
                     <hi>Quakers</hi> with, as for ſubverting the faith delivered by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and undermineing the hope of the Goſpell. He ſaith they ſubvert the faith in denying Chriſt to have that body in Heaven glorified in which he ſuffered and roſe again, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Reply, As for his lyes, and falſly accuſeing us about this (which will fall heavy upon his own head) they are clearly ſeen by many that know our beleefe in theſe things, wherin we own what the Scriptures do declare. And how doth this charge of <hi>I. H.</hi> againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> agree with his, and <hi>Tho. Moore</hi>'s ſaying in their Book: That we ſaid the ſame body that ſuffered was glorified at Gods right Hand in Heaven? when now he ſaith we deny Chriſt to have that body in Heaven glorified in which he ſuffered; Who will beleive this man's confuſion? who alſo ſaith in one of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers againſt us, that we are men of noe judgment about the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173002:7"/>Perſon of Chriſt. Now I ſay then if it were ſo, how ſhould we ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affirme or deny any thing about it? for if we do either, we muſt be of ſome judgment about it: And how ſhould we ſubvert any ones faith about the Perſon of Chriſt, if we be of no judgment about it? for if it were ſo with us, <hi>I. H.</hi> ſhould rather have infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us about the Perſon of Chriſt, to have brought us into ſome true judgment about it (if he could) then have charged us with preaching other Doctrins then the Apoſtles did, touching ſuch things as he hath falſly charged us to be of no judgment about. Thus his confuſion and falſhhood is apparent. For though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not own his and their imaginations, who have affirmed that Chriſt is in Heaven with a humane Body of fleſh and bones, without blood in it, wherein their blindneſſe much appears, and therin they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh not a ſpirituall Body from a humane Body, which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall or earthly, yet we owne that the Body of Chriſt which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and aſcended was changed. And ſo his Body is a ſpiritual glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Body in Heaven, in the nature of the ſame glory which he had with the Father before the world began, wherein he is glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, where that which was mortall is ſwallowed up of life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortallitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I. H.</hi> again chargeth us with ſubverting the hope of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, in denying the reſurrection of the bodies of men, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> This is another ſlander for we own the reſurrection of the bodies both of the juſt and unjuſt according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſee how again this accuſer is confounded, He and <hi>T. M.</hi> in a Paper to me ſay, That we we are of no judgment about the Reſurrection: To which I ſay, then how ſhould we either deny it, or affirm ought of it? Several other things hath <hi>I. H.</hi> alſo falſly accuſed us within in his fourth page, which I have anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed elſewhere: And to my ſaying that Chriſt bid, <hi>Be ye perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect, I. H.</hi> ſaith, Exhortations to things prove not thoſe things to be perfectly attained by any here, nor doth the Scripture ever ſay, Let not ſin be in you, as if men might get it all out, though it ſays, <hi>Let it not reign in your mortal bodies. Rep.</hi> Then if the things which Chriſt exhorted men to upon earth may not be perfectly attained by any here, to what end or effect was his Exhortation? What muſt men be under the commands after death which they had in their life time, and not till then fulfill them? Here's darkneſs indeed manifeſt, and the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173002:7"/>commands of God put afar off, and made of none effect by ſuch as are out of his love, for he that loveth God keepeth his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and is it not all one for the Scripture to ſay, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your heavenly Father is perfect,</hi> as if it ſaid, Let not ſin be in you? Or the ſame to ſay, <hi>Waſh you, make ye clean,</hi> or <hi>keep Gods Commandments,</hi> and love, and ſerve him with all your heart, ſoul, ſtrength and minde, which muſt be fulfilled, then what part of man muſt be a ſubject for ſin to dwell in, while he lives here, as <hi>J. H.</hi> would have it? if no part of man be a ſubject to ſin ſo long as he lives, then it cannot abide in him, as take away the body of it, and its members cannot remain. And to my ſaying that <hi>J. H.</hi> had not proved that the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them ſo long as they lived; he ſaith, How falſe that was, appears in what <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaid on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. To which I ſay that Scripture does not prove that the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them ſo long as they lived, for there its ſaid, <hi>Enter not into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy ſervant, O Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified;</hi> and what <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaid on this, will not prove that the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them while they lived, ſeeing the Scripture it ſelf doth not prove it, its no matter of his words who perverts the Scriptures, and that Scripture does not include the Saints as to prove them unjuſtified who were changed from that ſtate, wherein no man living could be juſtified in the ſight of God, and were come thorow the death, and the many trials and tribulations into the life and righteouſneſs of Chriſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were juſtified, and the Prophets of the Lord, who deſired the Lord to cleanſe them from their ſecret ſins, and from all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in their life time: they prayed not in vain, as this Prieſts Doctrine in effect accuſeth them, in his accuſing them to have ſin in them ſo long as they lived, for the Lord giveth the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous the deſires of their hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Again, <hi>J. Horn</hi> relates part of our Diſcourſe deceitfully and imperfectly in theſe words; <hi>Viz J. H.</hi> Was not <hi>Paul</hi> born of God when he ſays, <hi>We alſo that have the firſt fruits of the Spirit, even we our ſelves groan within our ſelves, waiting for the adoption, the redemption of the body;</hi> and then theſe words he lays down for <hi>G. W.</hi> his Anſwer, <hi>viz. Paul</hi> when he travelled, and was groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for deliverance, and waiting for the redemption of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, was not as yet born of God, but afterward he witneſſed a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173002:8"/>being redeemed from ſin, and then he was born, as a woman when ſhe is in travel to be delivered, the childe is not yet born. <hi>J. H.</hi> then ſays, People, I pray, did you ever hear of a woman in travel, before that woman was born, was there ever ſuch a thing? here he ſays all the people fell a laughing at <hi>G. W.</hi> and then <hi>J. H.</hi> urges 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Whoſoever beleeves that Jeſus is the Chriſt is born of God; Paul</hi> did beleeve Jeſus to be the Chriſt, when he was an Apoſtle and writ to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and then he ſaith, here <hi>George</hi> was pittifully put to it, and all the people generally ſee his confuſion, and ſaith that <hi>G. W.</hi> was pittifully ſhackled and nonpluſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>John Horne</hi> hath both belyed me, and wronged my words, and left out the greateſt part of what I ſaid, that cleared my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the underſtandings of ſuch as had any ſoberneſſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſſe in hearing the diſcourſe. And that People generally ſee my Confuſion, or that I was ſhackled and non-pluſt, theſe are ſome of <hi>I.H.</hi> his lyes and ſcornfull aſperſions caſt upon me, as many that heard the diſpute can witneſs againſt him for impudently belying and ſlandering me, the ſum of what I anſwered and chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended (though I could not have liberty to open what I ſaid ſo much there as here) it was thus, <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed the groaning and travelling in pain before the birth was born in him, or before he was born of God, or in the ſtate of him that is born of God (intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as in 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.) who cannot ſin, which <hi>Paul</hi> could when he did the evil he would not, even when he travelled in pain for deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the bondage of corruption, for where the ſon or birth from above is born, the glorious liberty of the ſons of God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, which the creature waited for, and there the travelling in pain for deliverance is ceaſed, and the bondage of corruption re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, for the travel is before the birth be brought forth; and as for my inſtancing the womans travelling in pain before the child was born, <hi>J.H.</hi> hath perverted my compariſon, it was not intended to prove that <hi>Paul</hi> was not born into the world (according to the fleſh) wherewith he travelled, as if a woman were not ſo born when in travail, but in reference to the travail before the birth which was from above was born, and according to what I ſaid, Chriſt ſpake when he ſaid to his diſciples, <hi>Ye ſhall weep and lament, but the world ſhall rejoyce, and ye ſhall be ſorrowful, but your ſorrow ſhall be turned into joy, a woman when ſhe is in travail hath ſorrow,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173002:8"/>becauſe her hour is come, but as ſoon as ſhe is delivered of the child, ſhe remembreth no more the anguiſh, for joy that a man is born into the world,</hi> Joh. 16.20. and ſo it was evident that the diſciples of Chriſt knew the travail in the ſorrow before the man or birth from above was born in them, and they believed and hoped when they were in travail and pain before they became that birth, for that birth is free, and is not that which travails in pain; for that is in bondage while in pain, before the birth is brought forth to reign, which brings to the healing and to the reſt in the glorious liberty; which before that ſtate was witneſſed, even the Prophets alſo knew the travelling in pain, for thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>We have heard a voice of trembling, of fear, and not of peace, aske ye now and ſee whether a man man doth travail with childe, wherefore do I ſee every man with his hands on his loyns as a woman in travel, and all faces are turned into paleneſs,</hi> Jer. 30.6. <hi>And like as a woman with child that draweth near the time of her delivery is in pain and cryeth out in her pangs, ſo have we been in thy ſight O Lord, we have been with childe, we have been in pain,</hi> Iſa. 26.17. but when the Prophet witneſſed that unto them a child was born, and to them a ſon was given, who was the wond reful Counſellor, he brought the peace, and ended the travail and pain, he being the Prince of peace; but theſe ſtates I finde <hi>J. H.</hi> never knew, for to my knowledge he hath judged our ſpeaking of a babe within, but to be a dream, and is in his ſcorn, and lies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by making many of the people light and vain againſt the truth like the falſe Prophets: And where he ſaith, that here all the people fell a laughing at <hi>G. W.</hi> In this he would make all the people ignorant, and ſcoffers like himſelf, and herein many of the people who were at our diſpute can witneſs againſt this <hi>J. Horne</hi> for wickedly belying them alſo, for there were many both of our friends and others who were ſober minded, and did not joyn with him nor them of his company that ſcoffed in their laughter and ſcorn, which did much manifeſt his ſhame and theirs who therein joyned with him, ſeeing he was ſuch a bad example among ſo many hundreds of people, ſoberneſs and ſeriouſneſs might better have become him in reaſoning about the things of God.</p>
               <p>Again <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaith, I flew to another ſhift, for that <hi>Paul</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended in his writing to thoſe of low degree: to the ſtate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173002:9"/>of ſome he writ to, (as if the believing Romans or Saints at <hi>Rome</hi> were not borne of God, or did not then believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt) &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> As for his urging, that whoſoever be lieves that Jeſus is the Chriſt, is borne of God, he hath done it without under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and without diſtinction, though it be true according to <hi>Iohns</hi> Teſtimony of a true beleever, who by faith hath victory over the world. and ſo being borne of God is not under the bondage of corruption, nor can ſuch a one ſin becauſe he is borne of God, and his ſeed remaineth in him, ſo he witneſſeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, in ſaving him from ſin; but ſuch, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born of God <hi>I. H.</hi> doth not own while men are here; and let me tell him, that a man muſt believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, and believe in him too before he be borne of God, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Beleeve in the light, that ye may be the children of the light,</hi> John 12.36. ſo as for his urging, that whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, is born of God, without any true diſcerning or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction to ſuch a multitude of people, to make them believe that he had ſhackled me, herein his deceit was clearly ſeen; for what people is there of any underſtanding in the whole <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom,</hi> (and even among theſe Prieſts in <hi>England,</hi> whom this Prieſt <hi>Horne</hi> hath called greedy dumb dogs, ſtrong to appetite) that do not beleeve that Jeſus is the Chriſt? are they therefore born of God? examine and ſee. And that <hi>Paul</hi> condeſcended to the <hi>Romans</hi> to ſeverall States which he had paſſed thorow, and which were below his owne when he writ to them is evident, (for which thing affirming, this ſcornfull Prieſt hath ſo much reproached me) For <hi>Paul ſpake unto them after the manner of men, becauſe of the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their fleſh, Rom.</hi> 6.19. and he could not then be in all thoſe ſtates, (as in relation to his own particular condition) which he condeſcended to the <hi>Romans</hi> as one in: For he ſpake to them as one under the Law, and as a wretched man, and as one that did evill, who was led captive to the Law of ſin in his members, and asked who ſhould deliver him, like one that did not know who ſhould: though then he knew his deliverer, and deliverance, having bin a Miniſter many years, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.23. And he ſaid, <hi>I know that in me, that is in my Fleſh dwelleth no good thing,</hi> and yet was not Chriſt then in him, and in his Fleſh? and he ſpake unto them as in the warfare, in the pain,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173002:9"/>and bondage, and as one who found not how to perform that which was good; which ſtates, as in relation to his own conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he had paſſed thorough, for he was at peace with God, and freed from under the Law, and dead unto ſin, and ſo free from it, be being a Servant of Chriſt, and one who was more then a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, even when he writ to the <hi>Romans.</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. and <hi>chap.</hi> 6. and 7. and 8. ſo that any that underſtand theſeſt ates may ſee that <hi>Paul</hi> condeſcended to many ſtates below his own: for when he was free from all men he made himſelf ſervant unto all, that he might gain the more; for he ſaith unto the Jewes, I became as a Jew that I might gain the Jewes, and to them that are under the Law, as under the Law, that I might gain them that are under the Law; and to them that are without Law, (being not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law to God, but under the Law to Chriſt) that I might gain them that are under the Law; And to the weak became I as weak, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20: And ſo what I ſpake, touching <hi>Pauls</hi> travel and condeſcending was true, and upon good grounds, though <hi>J.H.</hi> and ſome of his company were ſo uncivil towards me in their bawling or wrangling, many of them at once againſt me, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding many Queſtions together upon me, at the diſpute (ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times) before I had explained my ſelf to one, and they would have tied me to Anſwer them Yea or Nay, when often the things queſtioned did of neceſſity admit of a larger Anſwer then Yea or Nay, ſhewing themſelves both to want moderation and true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and they would not ſuffer me ſeveral times to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain what I laid down as I would, for their bawling and heap of Queſtions, though <hi>J.H.</hi> durſt anſwer to very few Queſtions that I put to him; and as for his accuſing me, as that I would faine have bin reading in their Book, to have diverted from his Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, (or turned off from the diſcourſe in hand) In that I would not have long bin off the diſcourſe, for I would only have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them one or two of their Apparent Lies, and then have diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted further with him, but like guilty perſons neither he nor <hi>T. M.</hi> would let me then reade one clauſe of their own Book, though <hi>I. H.</hi> ſoon after fell a reading in one of ours, and falſely interpreted our words, as is hereafter diſcovered, and when they were ſo afraid, to ſuffer me to reade one particular in their book, many there took notice of their deceit, though I was content to diſpute on with him, when they would not ſuffer me to reade it,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173002:10"/>for I feel the Power of the Lord over them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I. H.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Then it ſeems</hi> Paul <hi>wrote a Lie as touching himſelf, that he waited for the Redemption of the body, and travelled in pain, when it was falſe of him, he did not ſo.</hi> I Anſwer, nay, do any charge <hi>Paul</hi> with falſhood but <hi>J. H. Paul</hi> writ true, for as he could condeſcend to the low eſtate of others, he could weep with them that weep, and wait and travel with them that waited for the Redemption of the body where it was not redeemed; and as he travelled for the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that Chriſt might be formed in them, when he knew Chriſt already formed in him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Did</hi> Paul <hi>then witneſſe or experiment the Redemption of his body from corruption before he died?</hi> and then he asks, <hi>Is not the body ſown in corruption when it dies? It is ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption.</hi> And again he asks, <hi>but is not that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption which is in death, in which the body corrupteth? and did not</hi> Paul <hi>wait for the Redemption of his body from that, and ſo he tells of the corruption of mortality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here again is a piece of this <hi>J. Horns</hi> deceit, in leaving out the word <hi>bondage,</hi> which I uſed in ſpeaking of the creatures Redemption from the bondage of corruption, and that <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed the Redemption of the body from the bondage of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, when the creature was delivered into the glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſons of God, and this the Saints had before their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe: and here <hi>J. H.</hi> ſo much urging, as that <hi>Paul</hi> waited for the Redemption of the body from the corruption in which it is ſowen in death, the corruption of mortality, in which the body corrupteth. This manifeſts, that he cannot diſcern between the bondage of corruption upon earth, and the natural corruption of a dead body in the grave, as if that corruption of the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in the grave were the bondage of corruption which cauſed the whole Creation to groan, and which <hi>Paul</hi> waited for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the body from, when he lived upon earth, was ever ſuch confuſion and folly uttered by a Teacher as is by this <hi>J. H.</hi> herein? for did <hi>Paul</hi> wait for his body to be redeemed from the corruption of mortality, in which it was ſown in the Grave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was in it? and needed he wait and travel for ſuch a Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his life-time? it is abſurd that <hi>J. H</hi> about this hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, which people may ſee, that he, and ſuch as own his principles, do count the bondage of corruption (which <hi>Paul</hi> waited
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173002:10"/>for the redemption of the body from) the corruption in which the body corrupteth in the grave, and ſo would make men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that <hi>Paul</hi> waited for the redemption of the body from that corruption of the body in death before it was in it, and that his body is not redeemed from the bondage of corruption till it be raiſed again out of the grave, ſo that from this then <hi>Paul</hi> is not yet come to the redemption of his body which ſo many hundred years he groaned and waited for, ſeeing that reſurrection of the bodies is not yet come, ſo you may here ſee that this Prieſt <hi>Horn</hi> hath not ſpoken the language and doctrine delivered by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and therefore is not to be liſtened to, nor followed, but to be accounted accurſed, according to his own ſentence, it muſt be meaſured to him again, for <hi>Paul</hi> groaned, not for that he would have been uncloathed, but <hi>cloathed upon,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. and the redemption of the body was the adoption which the Saints waited for through the Spirit of adoption, and which they received, ſeeing for that end God ſent forth his Son made of a woman made under the Law, <hi>to redeem them that were under the Law, that we might receive the adoption of ſons,</hi> Gal. 4 4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaith, <q>Well <hi>George,</hi> hitherto I have made good my charge, That you come not as the true Prophets and Apoſtles, thou haſt not been able to prove that any of them preached themſelves free from ſin, ſo as to be without ſin.</q> I reply here, <hi>I. H.</hi> hath again added to his former lies and folly; for how is his charge like to be made good by my not proving that the true Prophets and Apoſtles preached themſelves free from ſin, ſo as to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it (if I had not done it, but herein hath he ſpoken deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) but his charge ſhould rather have been made good if he had proved that all the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them, and were ſinners ſo long as they lived (according to his words) and then that we preach our ſelves free from ſin, and not to have confeſſed our ſins as the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did (which is according to his words or charge againſt us) which things he could never prove againſt us, for he knows not the confeſſions we have made of our ſins; and we preach not our ſelves perfect, as if our preaching made us perfect, or as if we were ſo of our ſelves, but we preach the work of Chriſt, which doth truly free from ſin and make perfect,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173002:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:173002:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:173002:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:173002:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:173002:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:173002:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:173002:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:173002:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:173002:15"/>and he it is that is made to us Righteouſneſſe and Perfection, who hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him be glory and dominion for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. And ſo <hi>I.H.</hi> his ſaying, that a man may be perfect in a Scripture-ſenſe, and yet have ſin. <hi>Aſa</hi>'s heart was perfect with the Lord all his dayes, and yet he ſinned. To which I ſay, It is not ſaid that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>'s heart was perfect all his life-time, for if it were, it might as well be ſaid he was perfect when he was in the natural ſtate, and when his heart was turned from the Lord, that he relied not on him, but on the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> for which the Prophet reproved him for dealing ſo fooliſhly: inſomuch that <hi>Aſa</hi> was in rage with him, and put him into priſon, and oppreſſed or cruſhed ſome of the people at that time, and when he was diſeaſed in his feet, he ſought not to the Lord, but to the Phyſicians; ſo could his heart be perfect with the Lord, when it was ſo far gone from the Lord? If any ſhall anſwer Yea, then I ſay, may it not as well be ſaid now of them who are oppreſſors and perſecutors of the ſervants of the Lord, and whoſe hearts are departed from the Lord? that their hearts are yet perfect with the Lord? So it being ſaid that <hi>Aſa</hi>'s heart was perfect with the Lord all his dayes, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. was intended while he did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, while the Land was kept quiet under his Reign: but after he departed from the Lord he had wars, for as <hi>Azariah</hi> ſaid unto them, the Lord is with you while you be with him, and if ye ſeek him, he will be found of you, but if ye forſake him, he will for ſake you, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. and ſaid <hi>Hanani</hi> the Seer unto <hi>Aſa, The eyes of the Lord run to and fro thorowout the whole earth, to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in behalf of them whoſe heart is perfect towards him: herein haſt thou dealt fooliſhly, therefore from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth thou ſhalt have wars;</hi> which manifeſts, that then his heart was not perfect towards the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.7. to the end.</p>
               <p>Oh! I ſee this <hi>J. H</hi> would willingly have men accounted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with the Lord, when they are ſinners; and if ſuch a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were, he would own it. But this will not ſerve his turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, for we own another kinde of perfection then he would have, not a perfection in the ſinful ſtate, or where men are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the Lord into the perſecuting nature, but ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as is enjoyed thorow the ſanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173002:15"/>where they that feare the Lord ſhall not depart from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And whereas <hi>I. H.</hi> tells a ſtory of one <hi>Giles Roſe</hi> (who came when we were in diſcourſe) whom he ſaith is a poor deluded man that was one of the firſt that turned Quakers in <hi>Lin,</hi> and that it hath been ſaid he objected ſometimes againſt them ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt carriages between ſome of their ſpeakers, and a woman of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The people hearing him (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſaid <hi>Giles</hi>) being at a diſtance like a kinde of a diſtracted man, <hi>I. H.</hi> ſaith, and <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> ſaid to me, ſee the fruit of thy Miniſtry <hi>George,</hi> thy prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are ready to lead men into diſtraction, and he ſaith the people laught, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> To which I ſay you may here ſee the malice and wickedneſs of the men in laying down (as they eount them) his words as an evidence againſt us; whom they count but as a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted man to render us odious to the world and to make them laugh at us: which ſo often <hi>I. H.</hi> hath boaſted in, and yet he hath ſome of this relation touching what the ſaid <hi>Giles</hi> ſhould ſay but by report of him, and not all from his own mouth as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, which ſheweth himſelf like one of the Prophets enemies who ſaid Report and we will Report, <hi>Ier.</hi> 20.10. and the things he hath given forth againſt us, as in that diſtracted mans name (as they count him) are lies and ſlanders, and will be the burthen of the inventers and ſpreaders of them; and as for that man, vvhom this <hi>Horne</hi> brings as a Witneſſe againſt us, he vvas for ſome time convinced of the truth, but running from his meaſure into his vain imaginations, friends diſovvned him, and then he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into envy sgainſt us, and ſo it is no matter vvhat he, and ſuch as beleeve him ſay againſt us, the truth in vvhich vve live (and our principles, vvhich are not any ground of diſtraction, as <hi>J.H.</hi> and <hi>T.M.</hi> accuſe them) ſhall ſtand for ever over all our enemies vvho hate the truth, and over all vvho turn into <hi>Judas</hi> vvay to perdition But <hi>J.H.</hi> vvho thus haſt ſhevved thy venome in ſpreading lies and ſlanders againſt us; doeſt thou think, if I vvould go about it, that I could not lay open much vvickedneſſe and ranting carriages, that have bin among you and ſeveral of thy company, and tell you of your Loves, and of a vvoman and her levvdneſſe, that vvas highly ſet up as a Preacher or Inſtructer among you, and ſeveral others? But I had rather be a ſufferer by you, then ſhame you, if you do not give me the more occaſion by your malice and ſlanders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth to lay you further open. <q>And now to <hi>Horns</hi> other part of his charge in his Argument where he ſaith thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:173002:16"/>They that undermine and deſtroy the hope of the Goſpell preached by the Apoſtles they are preachers of another Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell or doctrine then the Apoſtles, preached, and are to be accounted accurſed and not received or followed. This I charge you Quakers with, and you <hi>G. W.</hi> by name in that you ſay, the coming of Chriſt at which the dead in Chriſt are to be Raiſed is already paſt and over, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> I Anſwer, Here <hi>J. H.</hi> Thou haſt charged us exceeding falſely, and belyed us ſhamefully? for we never ſaid that the coming of Chriſt, at which the dead in Chriſt are to be raiſed is already paſt and over, but that the ſaints remained unto the coming of the Lord, as the Apoſtle ſaith, we which are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our words which thou haſt falſely and ſlanderouſly ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy charge upon, which are againſt thee and <hi>Thomas Moore,</hi> where we ſaid, as for that, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15. Concerning the coming of the Lord from heaven, which theſe men aforeſaid would blindly put afar off as to a coming of Chriſt with fleſh and bones, the Apoſtle ſaith we, which are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them which are aſleep; ſo that coming of Chriſt, the ſaints who then were alive remained unto it. To which <hi>John Horn</hi> ſaith, judge good people is Chriſt yet come, are <q>the dead bodies of the ſaints raiſed and the living changed, and all caught up together in the air to meet him? If theſe men be not ſuch as we are to avoid and account accurſed who be?</q> To which I ſay thus haſt thou wreſted our words, and made a falſe conſtruction of them, contrary to the end and intent of them; for what we ſaid was againſt your imaginations who look carnally for the coming of Chriſt as many of the world do, of whom Chriſt ſaid, I go away and the world ſeeth me no more, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. And I vindicated theſe ſaid words of ours mentioned, and witneſſed to the ſeverall comings of Chriſt as he was revealed in the ſaints from glory to glory; becauſe thou oppoſed theſe words to render us odious, and I never denied the coming of the Lord from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when he ſhall bring with him them that ſleep in Jeſus; and raiſe the dead in Chriſt, nor ever ſaid I that was already over and paſt as thou haſt belied me, for when I urged the Apoſtles re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining till the coming of the Lord as in, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15.17. Thou to render me odious urged, <hi>ver.</hi> 13.14.16. Which I never denied nor doubted of her, and ſo I ſlighted diſputing about it, though thou would have made it diſputable againſt me to make good thy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173002:16"/>charge and ſlander againſt me, and what confuſion would thou charge upon us, as to ſay the coming of Ghriſt, at which the dead in him are to be raiſed is already paſt and over, as if that which is yet to be vvere over and paſt, vvith this non-ſenſe thou might as vvell have charged the Saints as us: who remained unto the coming of the Lord, and yet did not prevent them vvhich were aſleep from being raiſed, though I did mention that of <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.25. touching the dead hearing the voice of the Son of God, that theſe that vvere dead or aſleep in their ſins might come to be raiſed out of them, and live; this I knevv vvas the moſt needful for many people that heard us, to knovv, they having ſuch as thou art for their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, vvhoſe Miniſtry doth greatly tend to keepe them in their ſins, when ſomuch they ſtrive for ſin, in contending and pleading for it, as thou haſt done. And in thy eleventh page thou haſt laid down many words in my name which I never ſpake, thy wickedly wronging me will come heavy upon thee one day. And oh! how lame and doubtfull is thy Relation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me? who when thou haſt oftentimes laid down anſwers for mine, thou ſayeſt, <hi>or to ſuch purpoſe was his anſwers,</hi> and ſo haſt but often gueſſed about my anſwers, and often belyed me, and perverted the words of truth, and broken my anſwers often, putting but peeces of them down, as any impartiall reader of thy relation who heard our diſpute may eaſily ſee. And after thou haſt for a pretence laid down part of my Anſwers, thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſayeſt, <hi>to ſuch purpoſe was his anſwer,</hi> but with more circumſtances, and tells of my running into a long circuling diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and ſo haſt left out many things I ſaid, which tendered much to the clearing of my anſwers, to the underſtandings of "the ſimple. And where I ſaid that of God in the people muſt be Judge, <hi>Iohn Horne</hi> ſaith, he appeals to that of God in them all. See what a diſſembling imitation he is in here how can he appeal to that of God in all the People, when he denyes that all have the light of Chriſt in them? which is that of God in all which we ſpeak of, and appeal to in all, and to my knovvledge this Prieſt hath often contended againſt our ſaying the light of Chriſt, or a ſpiritual light is in all men, vvhich is that in every one vvhich the true Miniſter muſt appeal to, and be a good ſavour to both, in them that are ſaved, and in them that periſh, which the blind guides of this Age do ſo much contend againſt. And where I laid upon this Prieſt <hi>Horn,</hi> his writing ſo much againſt the Prieſts of this Nation, and his calling them ſuch as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 56.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173002:17"/>Watchmen that are blinde greedly dogges, and dumbe dogs, &amp;c. when he himſelfe is in the ſame ſtepps they are in. To this he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies thus to me, <hi>viz. Nay George, thou doeſt not findt hee to the us dumb dogs, we are made able, bleſſed be God, to worry thee, and put worſt, &amp;o.</hi> and at the diſpute he told me he was able to worry me, and ſuch Foxes as I am, ſo you may ſee the falſhood and vanity of this man and his Reaſon: which is no better then to ſay, a dog that is a worrier is not a dumb dog, becauſe he can worry, when as the dumb dogs uſe to be the greateſt worriers, as the blind Watchmen in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were compared to ſuch, when they fed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſought for their gaine from their Quarters, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and ſcattered the Flock. So here <hi>J. H.</hi> hath not cleared himſelf from being one of the Watchmen whom he hath called dumb dogs, ſeeing that according to his own confeſſion he is a worrier, and ſo not as Chriſt<hi>'s</hi> Miniſters were, who were Lambs among Wolves. Again <hi>J. H.</hi> anſwers me thus, <hi>viz. The Lamb is a Lyon to</hi> George, <hi>and makes Iſrael a Lyon too. Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 49.9. <hi>Mica.</hi> 5.8. <hi>And it is in his strength and power, that we are inabled to tear and worry thee, &amp;c.</hi> To which I ſay, here again hath he falſly boaſted in his folly and falſhood, and of that power which he was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to be out of both in the diſpute, and when he ſought to break up the meeting, and fled out of it, before I would have had him, and left ſeverall Queſtions unanſwered which I put to him. And it's ſaid at the end of this his relation in the next page, <q>
                     <hi>that the Church-Warden M. H with other Friends, ſeing J. H. much ſpent with ſpeaking ſo long, and ſomuch, and fearing be might wrong himſelf therin, and that he being tyred, and much ſpent, withdrew, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> When a little before he boaſted of his being in the ſtrength and power of the Lion, and as a Lion that could tear and worry me, counting me a Fox, and now he is tyred and much ſpent, and he fain to flee for it, was ever the like confuſion and ignorance heard of? Did you ever hear of a Fox that out-ſtood a Lion ſo far in battle, as to cauſe the Lion to be ſo tired and much ſpent, that the Lion was firſt fain to flee for it, and ſo many of <hi>John Horns</hi> Friends who count themſelves in the ſtrength and power of the Lion were afraid he might wrong himſelf he being ſo much ſpent and tyred. You may ſee here that his boaſting of his God, and of his being in the Lions power is come to nought, and that he is a meer Hypocrite and diſſembler to boaſt of being in that which he is out of, and if we be Foxes, and he a tearer and a worrier according to his own words: how is it he cannot feare us, or affright us away?</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:173002:17"/>
               <p>And to that where it is ſaid, <hi>J. Horne</hi> and others of his friends, laughing at the Quakers, and <hi>G. W.</hi> to ſee ſome of his confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and to prove his laughing he brings, <hi>The righteous ſhall ſee them, and laugh them to ſcorn:</hi> I ſay, It hath in this thing large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted his folly and vanity, in his, and his companies laughing and ſcoffing among ſuch a great company, which did incourage prophane and ignorant people in their ſcorn and laughter, which is madneſs; which theſe Profeſſors ſtirred up in them, but many that were ſober ſaw their folly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs therein; ſo that <hi>J. H.</hi> was not a Miniſter of grace to the hearers, but of that which ſtirred up folly and madneſs among them. And now what impudence is he in, to boaſt of ſuch vanity and wickedneſs in print, and bring <hi>David</hi>'s words for a cover to it? when he never knew the ſtate of <hi>David,</hi> nor truly underſtands when to laugh, and when to mourn, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by his unſavory practices: So that the righteous who ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on high will laugh him to ſcorn, who hath ſcorned the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and cauſed others ſo to do as he hath done; and <hi>wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that laugh now, for they ſhall mourn and weep,</hi> Luk 6.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>J. H.</hi> accounts, that he is compleatly righteous, though in himſelf he acknowledges ſin, and for proof he ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid, <hi>Coloſ</hi> 2.10. <hi>In him yee are complete:</hi> and yet in the ſame Epiſtle to the ſame people, he ſaith; <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ifie therefore your members that be upon earth, fornication, uncleaneſs,</hi> &amp;c. If theſe were not in them, how could they be called their members upon earth? To which I ſaying the Apoſtles writing to the Churches, writ to diverſe ſtates, ſome of them were complete in Chriſt, and others were not, &amp;c. <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaith, the Apoſtle makes no ſuch diſtinction; and he ſaith, What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> think the Apoſtle writ one Chapter to one part of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and another Chapter to another?</q> 
                  <hi>Reply:</hi> The Apoſtle never ſaid that they that were in the fornication, uncleanneſs, inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections, evil concupiſcence, covetouſneſs, were then in that ſtate complete in Chriſt; for they that were complete in Chriſt had put off all theſe, and knew the old man with his deeds, and the body of the ſins of the fleſh put off, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.10, 11. &amp; 3 7, 8, 9, 10. So that the members of that body could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main where the body on which they were was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut off, and ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173002:18"/>the Apoſtles exhorting to mortifie their members which were upon earth; as fornication, uncleanneſs, in which they walked in time paſt, does not prove that all the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> were in the fornication, as follows from <hi>J. H.</hi> his words: who makes no diſtinction of the ſtate among theſe <hi>Paul</hi> writ to, but blindly cavills at me for diſtinguiſhing the diverſe ſtates when I diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed the ſtate of being complete in Chriſt, where the body of ſin is put off from the ſtate of fornication and uncleanneſs, and his asking, if the Apoſtle writ one Chapter to one part of the people, and another Chapter to another, does manifeſt his blindneſs; for the Apoſtles Epiſtles were not divided into Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters when he writ them, as now they are. And as for that 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. where it's ſaid, <hi>For there is no man that ſinneth not,</hi> which <hi>Jo. Horne</hi> and <hi>T. Moore</hi> have much cavilled at me for owning it but as belonging to that ſtate wherein all men were ſinners, and ſo <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is no man living ſinneth not, Jeſus Chriſt excepted.</hi> In this have they contradicted <hi>Johns</hi> words, who ſaid 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>Whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not, neither can he ſin;</hi> and he that abideth in Chriſt, ſinneth not: and he that doth righteouſneſs, is righteous, even as Chriſt is righteous; ſo that ſuch is not included in theſe words mentioned in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46, they knowing a better Covenant then that which the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites were under when that was ſpoken by <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46 and J. H. and T. M. in <hi>page</hi> 8. acknowledge, <hi>That they that are born of</hi> God <hi>cannot ſin,</hi> or do any thing againſt the truth: and that ſin dwelt in <hi>Paul,</hi> but it was not he that did it; ſo that this flatly contradicts his ſaying; There is no man living that ſinneth not; and their applying that Scripture, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. to them that cannot ſin, nor do any thing againſt the Truth, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cuſing ſuch with it, as being ſinners: Thus their confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and folly appears in ſtriving for the Divels Kingdom, by contending or pleading for his work, which is ſin, which Chriſt comes to deſtroy, and throughly to purge and ſanctifie the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from: who is the one offering by which God hath for ever perfected them that are ſancrified. And at the end of J. H. his Relation of the Diſcourſe between us, it's ſaid thus, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>[To ſuch purpoſe was the Diſcourſe between J. H. and G. W. we have here given the ſubſtance and ſcope, if not alſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173002:18"/>form of the Anſwers, and the very Words and form ſo much as could be remembred, &amp;c.]</q> To which I ſay, Here <hi>J. Horne</hi> ſeems as if he would make people believe, that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did not give forth the ſaid Relation, but ſome others, but then who theſe were is not mentioned; for they have not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed their names to it, and here it is but related doubtfully, as if the Relators thereof had but depended upon their own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, as relating ſo much of it as could be remembred: But dare J. H. ſay that he was not the Author of the ſaid lame and imperfect Relation of the Diſcourſe? nor the cauſe of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publiſhed? and that it was all as it is related in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars thereof, taken from our own mouths, as and when we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted? Let the Reader judge of his deceit in theſe things.</p>
               <p>And where in the ſaid Pamphlet it is ſaid, <q>
                     <hi>The wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeeming generally well ſatisfied againſt the Quakers, to the no ſmal trouble of the Quakers, as might be conceived for their coming divers of them in the next Lords-day after with</hi> G. W. <hi>to the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Theſe are more of the lies which <hi>J. H.</hi> boaſts in, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that heard our diſcourſe (who ſaw the truth over him, in which we had peace, and were not at all troubled) can witneſs againſt theſe things as lies, and that diverſe of the Quakers came with me on that day to the Congregation, is falſe: for I went alone to the Steeple-houſe, and their coming was not known to me before I went, though they came, deſiring to ſee what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of me there; and ſo they ſaw the abuſe that ſome of this <hi>J. H.</hi> his hearers did againſt me, in not ſuffering me to ſpeak to them in the Steeple houſe when he had done, but violently pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me down, tore off my Hat, and haled me out; inſomuch that many that were not of the Quakers, ſpake againſt them for it, and would have had me ſpoken: and as a friend told me that day, an Alderman of their own company ſaid to him, as that if I went again to that Congregation hee feared I ſhould receive harme or prejudice to my perſon, though I did not look out at that. And whereas I ſaid I had a word from the Lord to the people, J. H. in his Poſtſcript doth declare, <q>[That he judg it as well done in thoſe perſons in power, not to ſuffer the ſaid G. W. to utter his pretended Word from the Lord: and that it is well done of the people not to hear it:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173002:19"/>and that they ſhall do evil, if hereafter they any of them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to ſpeak, and much more if they hear and liften to me, or any of us in ſuch way of doctrine, he ſaith.]</q> To which I ſay then J.H. would incourage thoſe perſons in power to perſecute me, and to cauſe the outward man to ſuffer (upon the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion it ſeems) and thus he would ſtop the witneſs of God in me (which torments him) from ſpeaking: though it was not the perſons in power (<hi>viz.</hi> the Magiſtrates) that did ſo abuſe me in his Steeple-houſe, as I was abuſed, for ſome of them in power indeavoured to preſerve me from the abuſe of them that did chiefly abuſe me, and the people did hear me in the Yard, contrary to this Prieſt's words and mind: But if neither <hi>J. Horne</hi> nor any of his hearers, (according to his direction to them) muſt permit me to ſpeak, then from this, they muſt either cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſh me ſome way or other, to ſtop my mouth, or elſe they muſt murther me; how ſhould they hinder me from ſpeakingels? And here he hath not onely included himſelf as one that muſt perſecute me to hinder me from ſpeaking; but alſo he hath given liberty to the people who are not in power or authority, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me, as if he were ſome great tyrannizing Magiſtrate, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting himſelf to be in <hi>Cain's</hi> Way: So whether this Prieſt <hi>Horne</hi> doth intend with his Hearers to proceed lawfully againſt me, ot not, the People may eaſily judge; for which I leave him to the Lord to be judged for his malice herein. And here alſo you may ſee that J.H. was not able to tear nor woory me, nor to ſtop my mouth with his words, as falſly he would boaſt, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is fain to encourage them in power, &amp; the people to hinder me from ſpeaking: And this is the beaſtly ſhift theſe ſilly Prieſts are fain to flee to when their Goſpel will not defend them; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can their God give them victory by it.</p>
               <p>And J.H. ſaith, As for this People the <hi>quakers,</hi> unleſs they ſee and turn from their evil Way, God's hand will be againſt them, and that their root is rottenneſs, and ſhall be dried and periſh, he ſaith.</p>
               <p>To which I ſay, <hi>J. Horne</hi> hath but here judged us in his malice, and propheſied from the envy of his own heart, and we doubt not but his Propheſie will prove falſe, and come to paſs upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173002:19"/>himſelf; and many ſuch lying Prophets againſt us as he is, there is in the World; and if our root were rottenneſs, how is it we we are ſuch a heavy judgement, burthen and torment to him, and ſuch deceivers as he is? And how is it we encreaſe and grow ſo much in the power of God, that our Borders are ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, that We are a burthen to our Enemies, ſuch falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and blind Watchmen as J H. is, who with his Brother <hi>T.M.</hi> hath acknowledged us to be a heavy Judgement that God hath ordered to puniſh them for their neglect of Chriſt, and the abuſe of his Truth; and yet ſince he hath boaſted of their being able to woory and tear me, and now accuſeth our root to be rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; which is as much as if they had ſaid, They can woory and tear the heavy Judgement that God hath ordered to them, and that the <hi>R</hi>oot of that judgement is rottenneſs, according to this Prieſt H<hi>orn's</hi> own Words; and herein hath he ſadly blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt God, who is the root of his own Judgements; one of whoſe Judgements we are ordered by him to puniſh J.H. and ſuch as he is, for their neglect of Chriſt, and the abuſe of his Truth; and therefore we muſt do the Work that God hath ſent us for: And what preſumption is it of J.H. to perſwade his Hearers not to permit us to ſpeak, nor to liften to us, but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count us accurſed, when we are the heavy Judgement that God ordered to puniſh them for their abuſe of his truth, vvhich is all one as if he had ſaid, Permit not God to ſpeak by his Judgement to us, nor liſten to the Judgement that God hath ordered to puniſh us for our our faults, but account it accurſed. And thus his blaſphemy and hardneſs of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt is manifeſt, like theirs vvho repented not of their evil deeds, (ſpoken of in <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9. but blaſphemed againſt the God of Heaven vvhen they vvere in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the Plagues of God, vvhoſe Judgements are all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous upon the diſobedient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>J. H.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The King Chriſt ſhall rejoice in God, and every one that ſwears by (or confeſſeth) him ſhall glory,</hi> Pſal. 63.10. <hi>Let them alone, neither abuſe them with incivilities, &amp;c.</hi> To which I ſay, If every one that ſwears by Chriſt ſhall glory, then muſt the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards and Liars, and all ſuch prophane perſons as ſwearby him, glory; and ſo this doctrine of his tends to the incouraging of Drunkards, and profane perſons in ſwearing, which is againſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173002:20"/>the Doctrine of Chriſt, who put an end to the Oaths and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which was under the Lavv, where there vvas ſvvearing by the Lord; for Chriſt and the Apoſtle commanded not to ſvvear at all: and he that tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath not. And if people muſt let us alone, and not abuſe us vvith incivilities, then J. H. and his company ought to permit us to ſpeak, and he ought not encourage them to perſecute us, as he hath done a little before: thus he ſtill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers his ovvn confuſion, whereby he hath ſo long abuſed the Truth of God, and been fighting againſt the heavie Judgment of God (vvhich is his due) as he hath done, vvho by his carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Doctrine hath encouraged drunkards, ſcoffers and ſvvearers in their vvickedneſs. Thus all that come to the Truth may ſee hovv evill men and ſeducers vvax vvorſe and vvorſe.</p>
               <p>And to theſe words in <hi>J. H.</hi> his Pamphlet, which are thus laid down, <hi>viz. Our Lord Jeſus teaching his Diſciples to pray to God as their Father, and in the firſt place to breathe or deſire the hallowing or ſanctifying of Gods Name, the coming of his Kingdom, and that his will might be done in earth as it is in heaven, and yet teaching them to pray for forgiveneſs of their treſpaſſes; doth he not ſtrongly and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imply, that even ſuch as are the children of God, and ſo born of God, and that have their hearts through his grace, ſet for the glory of God's Name above all things, and ſo for the coming of his Kingdom, and the doing of his will, have ſins and treſpaſſes againſt</hi> God, <hi>of which they need forgiveneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; Men may call God Father, as he is the Creator of all: <hi>Mal.</hi> 2 10. before they are born of God, or before the birth which is from above, be brought forth in them, which is indued with power from on high; and before the Diſciples were endued with that power, or come to that ſtate, they were to pray for the forgiveneſs of their treſpaſſes: Now that which was in the Treſpaſſes, was not the Seed in them which the Promiſe was to; neither in that ſtate was the Seed brought forth to reign, while the firſt Birth or treſpaſſer againſt God which the Law takes hold upon, was alive and acting them; and no man can truly call God Father, but by the Holy Ghoſt; and that which called him Father in the Diſciples of Chriſt, (when they were begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the belief of the Truth) was begotten of him; and they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173002:20"/>praying in that (as being begotten before they were in the ſtat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of him that is born of God, as mentioned in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3) they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived what they asked, and ſo came to have their treſpaſſes for given as they forgave others theirs, and to inherit the Kingdom of God and his Power, which they prayed for, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14 <hi>Rev.</hi> 12 10. In which Kingdom there is no ſinne, nor unclean thing can come; and they that are come to the childrens ſtate, that are born of God and abide in Chriſt, they ſin not; and the childrens ſtate muſt be witneſſed, before the Kingdom be inherited; alſo there may be children begotten, and not in that which is born of God, nor in the Kingdome, if they abide not in the Seed; ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> travelled for, that Chriſt might be formed in them.</p>
               <p>J.H. again ſaith, <hi>Or is it not evident that our Saviour teacheth thus to pray, till his Name be perfectly every where hallowed, his Kingdom fully come, and his Will perfectly done every where, even in earth as in heaven, which is not in this world,</hi> ſaith he.</p>
               <p>I anſwer; Why ſhould Chriſt teach his to pray that his Will may be perfectly done every where, even in earth, as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, if it be not in this World ſo to be done? What darkneſs is this <hi>J.</hi> H. in, and confuſion? And how hath he herein appeared againſt the end for which the Diſciples of Chriſt prayed as he taught them, who prayed that the Fathers Will might be done in Earth as in Heaven, which this Prieſt hath denied to be in this World; but Chriſts Teſtimony contradicts him; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>What things ſoever ye deſire when ye pray, believe that ye receive them, and ye ſhall have them, Mark</hi> 11.23, 24. And they deſired the Will of God to be done in Earth, as in Heaven, where there is no ſin.</p>
               <p>J. H. ſaith, <hi>But by adding the Prayer for daylie Bread, and that before Prayer for forgiveneſs of their Treſpaſſes; doth he not imply that ſo long as men have need of Bread for their life, they have alſo need to pray for pardon of, and keeping from ſin: if then the</hi> quakers <hi>(ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) will ſay they have no ſin in them, let them manifeſt it in living without Bread or food, and we may then (it may be) think there is ground to believe them, that the Name of God is ſo hallowed, his Kingdom ſo come, and his will ſo done in them, that they have no ſin nor treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:173002:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here <hi>J.</hi> H. hath ſhewed himſelf to be a ſcornful temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a blind unbeliever; For Chriſt when upon earth did eat Bread and Food, but that did not argue that he had ſin; and he hath left us an example that his ſteps ſhould be followed who did not ſin, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 21, 22. And how ſhall men pray for keeping from ſin, if they may not be kept from it, according to J. H. his Words, who alſo would make Chriſts praying of none effect, if none may be kept from ſin; for Chriſt prayed to the Father that his children might be kept from the evil, even in the World, and be perfect in one as he and his Father were one, <hi>John</hi> 17. And twhen ſome of the <hi>quakers</hi> have faſted certain dayes together as they were moved, (and as many of Gods People have done) and been upheld in it by the Power of God, ſome of this generation of tempters have ſlandered them, as being in deluſion or Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft; and one partaking of their iniquities is this Prieſt <hi>Horne,</hi> and he ſaith that they may (it may be) think there is ground to believe us if we will live without bread or food: It appears its but doubtful whether they'l believe us or not, if ſuch a thing might be: Thus J.H. thy folly and deceit is gone abroad: Oh! groſs darkneſs is thy Habitation.</p>
               <p>J. H. ſaith, <hi>Note, whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not; whoſoever is perfectly born of God, as the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, that is deceaſed, they cannot ſin; nor the men when their ſpirits and bodies ſhall be re-united in the Reſurrection; but none are ſo perfectly born of God here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Oh what pitiful ſtuff is here, to imagine that men are not perfectly born of God, ſo as not to ſin, till they are decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and when their ſpirits and bodies ſhould be re-united in the Reſurrection! And this would make the work of God imperfect here, when all his Works are perfect: And what were theſe that were born of God in the Apoſtles dayes, (who the Apoſtle ſaid, could not ſin) ſome that were deceaſed and riſen again, having their bodies and ſpirits re-united then in the Reſurrection (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what J.H. ſpeaks?) Surely J. H. had I ſaid as much as thou haſt done herein, thou might well have ſaid that I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the hope of the Goſpel; and much more of thy confuſion and lyes have I left unmentioned here.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:173002:21"/>
               <p>And where J.H. ſaith, that G.F. and G.W. uncivilly poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d him up as going away on purpoſe (intending that they poſted him up as going on purpoſe out of <hi>Lin</hi> to avoid diſputing with them) this is falſhood: For what we poſted up, had not thoſe words in it, but was a true Relation to certifie the people why we could not then have a publike meeting (as we demanded) neither with J.H. nor T.M. that they might not think that the canſe of our not meeting with them at that time, did lie upon our parts, but upon theirs, and this was occaſioned by J.H. his many ſlanderous Papers which he poſted up before, wherein he charged the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> with being dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivers and accurſed; and in ſome of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers he promiſed to make that charge good, as, and when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lawfully called; which he hath not yet done, nor can do.</p>
               <p>Some of J. H. his Doctrines and ſlanders againſt us, are here again laid down, which all that are ſober-minded who read this, may judge of, and ſee that he hath not made them good againſt us.</p>
               <p>One particular he urged, and in effect affirmed, was, <hi>That the corruption which Paul groaned and waited for the redemption of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from, was the corruption of Mortality in which the body is in death when it is in corruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Prophets and Apoſtles had ſin in them ſo long as they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Scriptures never ſayes, Let not ſin be in you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That there is no man living that ſinneth not, Jeſus Chriſt excepted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Quakers are deceivers, and ſuch as the People ought not to hear, but to account them accurſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they</hi> (to wit, the <hi>Quakers) come not as the true Prophets and Apoſtles did, viz. With abaſements of themſelves, and lifting up God and Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they ſubvert the Faith, in ſaying that the knowledge of Chriſt that is to eternal ſalvation, is the knowledge of him after the Spirit, as he was before the world was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they deny the reſurrection of the bodies of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they deny Chriſt to have that body in heaven glorified, in which he ſuffered and roſe again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Quakers ſay, the coming of Chriſt in which he ſhall deſcend with a ſhout, with the voice of the Arch-Angel, and the Trump of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173002:22"/>God, and when the dead in Chriſt ſhall be raiſed, and the living belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers be changed, is over and paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J.H. ſaid, he is not a dumb dog, for he is able to tear and woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me, and ſuch Foxes.</p>
               <p>Now theſe his charges againſt us called <hi>quakers,</hi> which are but a few of his many ſlanders, I return them back upon him, and reject them as lyes and ſlandars; and if he further aſſay to make them good, I ſhall know further how to proceed againſt him, as the Lord ſhall make way; for I have much more of his confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, falſe doctrines and ſlanders, which are not yet gone abroad, which I have noted, and are upon Record:</p>
               <p>One thing more I note, That the ſaid <hi>J. Horne</hi> and <hi>T. Moore</hi> in a Paper againſt me, ſay (of us called <hi>quakers</hi>) That we be indeed Vipers and Scorpions, Cockatrices not to be charmed, and like the Locuſts out of the bottomleſs pit, whoſe ſting is in their Tales, they ſay: And yet theſe men that have thus reproached us, have confeſſed that we are a heavy judgement that God hath ordered to them, to puniſh them for their neglect of Chriſt the ſalvation of God, and the Truth of him ſo long abuſed by them. Novv from their ovvn confeſſion they are ſuch as have not the ſeal of God upon their foreheads; for the Locuſts were onely ſent to puniſh theſe men that had not the ſeal of God upon their foreheads; <hi>Rev.</hi> 94. Thus their malice and confuſion is gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, who ſhall know one day that we are another manner of Judgement againſt them, then the Locuſts; and the more they ſtrive againſt the heavy Judgement that God hath ordered to puniſh them for the neglect of Chriſt, and abuſing of his Truth, the greater will their ſhame and torment be.</p>
               <p>And all People in whom there is a ſimplicity of Truth appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and a deſire ſtirring in you after life for your ſouls, beware of the Leaven of theſe Deceivers and abuſers of the Truth, who are ſo contending and pleading for ſinne, whereby the Devils Kingdom is upheld and ſtrengthened, and his ſubjects encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in his ſervice; for the hand of the Lord is againſt them, and God will aſſuredly confound and overthrow them; their confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and folly is already much gone abroad, therefore feed not you upon their confuſion, nor upon their chaff (dead words) but come off from among theſe barren Mountains, and heed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173002:22"/>the appearance of the Light of the Lord in you, and feel it, that you may come to the bread of Life, and to feed upon the fleſh of Chriſt which comes down from Heaven: For the Lord is exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his holy Mountain above all the barren Mountains that have lifted up themſelves againſt him. Bleſſed are they that come into the love of the Truth, and wait in the Light of it in them, whereby they may be undeceived, and eſcape out of the ſnares of ſuch ungodly men who make a prey upon ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
